<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England and Scotlands covenant with their God in viz, the protestation, the vow, and covenant, and an ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament for the taking the same / ordered by the Commons in Parliament that these covenants and ordinances bey forthwith printed and published.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07916303</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07916303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40426</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38366)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40426)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1205:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England and Scotlands covenant with their God in viz, the protestation, the vow, and covenant, and an ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament for the taking the same / ordered by the Commons in Parliament that these covenants and ordinances bey forthwith printed and published.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Husband,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Together with an exhortation made by the Assembly of Divines, an ordinance for the better observation of the Lords-day, an ordinance together with an order for the strict keeping the monthly fast."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40426:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40426:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLAND AND SCOTLANDS <hi>COVENANT</hi> With their GOD;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>In
<list>
                     <item>The <hi>Proteſtation,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The <hi>Solemn League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>and an Ordinance of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for the taking the ſame; together with an <hi>Exhortation</hi> made by the Aſſembly of DIVINES.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>An <hi>Ordinance</hi> for the better Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Lords-Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Ordinance,</hi> together with an <hi>Order,</hi> for the ſtrict keeping the <hi>Monthly faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ORdered by the Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That theſe Covenants and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Edw. Husband,</hi> Printer to the Honorable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:40426:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40426:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Mercurii,</hi> 5. <hi>Maii,</hi> 1641.</head>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Houſe of Commons now Aſſembled in Parliament, That the Preamble, together with the Proteſtation which the Members of this Houſe made the third day of <hi>May,</hi> ſhall be forthwith Printed, and the Copies Printed brought to the Clerk of the ſaid Houſe to atteſt under his hand, to the end, that the Knights, Citizens, and But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes may ſend them down to the Sheriffs and Iuſtices of Peace of the ſeverall Shires, and to the Citizens and Burgeſſes of the ſeverall Cities, Boroughs and Cinque Ports reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively; And the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, are to intimate unto the Shires, Cities, Boroughs and Cinque Ports, with that willingneſſe all the Members of this Houſe made this Proteſtation: And further to ſignifie, that as they juſtifie the taking of it in themſelves, ſo they cannot but approve it in all ſuch as ſhall take it.</p>
            <div type="protestation">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40426:3"/>
               <p>VVE the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe of Parliament, finding to the great grief of our hearts, that the Deſignes of the Prieſts and Ieſuites, and other adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> have of late been more boldly and frequently put in practice then formerly, to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining and danger of the ruine of the true Reformed Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in His Majeſties Dominions eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: And finding alſo that there have been, and having juſt cauſe to ſuſpect that there ſtill are, even during the ſitting in Parliament, endeavours to ſubvert the Fundamentall Laws of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to introduce the exerciſe of an Arbitrary and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall Government, by moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious and wicked Counſels, Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Plots, and Conſpiracies: And that the long intermiſſion, and unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py breach of Parliaments, hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned many Illegall Taxations, whereupon the Subject hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and grieved: And that divers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40426:3"/> Innovations and Superſtitions have been brought into the Church, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes driven out of His Majeſties Dominions; jealouſies raiſed and ſomented betwixt the King and His People; a Popiſh Army levied in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and two Armies brought into the bowels of this Kingdom, to the hazard of His Majeſties Royall Perſon, the conſumption of the Revenues of the Crown &amp; Treaſure of this Kingdom: And laſtly, finding great cauſe of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, that endeavours have been, and are uſed to bring the Engliſh Army into a miſunderſtanding of this Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, thereby to incline that Army, with force to bring to paſſe thoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked councels, Have therefore thought good to joyn themſelves in a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our united Affections and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and to make this enſuing Proteſtation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="oath">
               <p>I <hi>A. B.</hi> do in the preſence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, Promiſe, Vow, and Proteſt, to maintain and defend, as far as lawfully I may, with my life, power, and eſtate, the true Reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40426:4"/> Religion, expreſſed in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Popery and Popiſh Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions within this Realm, contrary to the ſame Doctrine, and according to the duty of my Alleagiance, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Royall perſon, Honour and Eſtate; as alſo the Power and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament; The lawfull Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and every perſon that maketh this Proteſtation, in whatſoever he ſhall do in the lawfull purſuance of the ſame. And to my power, and as far as lawfully I may, I will oppoſe, and by all good wayes and means endeavour to bring to condigne puniſhment, all ſuch as ſhall either by Force, Practiſe, Councels, Plots, Conſpiracies, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, do any thing to the contrary of any thing in this preſent Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion contained. And further, That I ſhall in all juſt and Honorable wayes endeavour to preſerve the Vnion and Peace, between the three Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> And neither for hope, fear, nor other reſpect, ſhall relinquiſh this Promiſe, Vow, and Proteſtation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40426:4"/>
               <p>VVHereas ſome doubts have been raiſed by ſeverall perſons out of this Houſe, concerning the meaning of theſe words contained in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation lately made by the Members of this Houſe, <hi>Viz. The true Reformed Proteſtant Religion, expreſſed in the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>againſt all Popery and Popiſh innovations within this Realm, contrary to the ſame Doctrine;</hi> This Houſe doth Declare That by thoſe words, was, and is meant, onely the publike Doctrine profeſſed in the ſaid Church, ſo far as it is oppoſite to Popery and Popiſh Innovations; And that the ſaid words are not to be extended to the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of any Form of Worſhip, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, or Government, nor of any Rites or Ceremonies of the ſaid Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="resolution">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40426:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Die Veneris,</hi> 30. <hi>Iulii,</hi> 1641.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolved upon the Question,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THat this Houſe doth conceive that the Proteſtation made by them, is fit to be taken by every perſon that is well-affected in Religion, and to the good of the Common wealth; And therefore doth declare, That what perſon ſoever ſhall not take the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, is unfit to bear Office in the Church or Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="covenant">
            <head>The <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament, to be taken by every Man, in the Cities of <hi>London, Westminſter,</hi> the Suburbs and Liberties thereof; and throughout the whole Kingdom.</head>
            <p>VVHereas the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons now aſtembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have declared, That there hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40426:5"/> been, and now is a Popiſh and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Plot for the ſubverſion of the true Proteſtant Reformed Religion, and the Liberty of the Subject; and that in purſuance thereof, a Popiſh Army hath been raiſed, and now is on foot in divers parts of this Kingdom: And have further in a ſolemn manner Declared, Vowed, and Covenanted, That in order to the ſecurity and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Liberty of the Subject, they will not conſent to the laying down of Arms, ſo long as the Papiſts now in open War againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall by force of Arms be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected from the Juſtice thereof. And whereas the Lords and Commons have Declared, That there hath been a treacherous and horrid Deſign lately diſcovered, by the great bleſſing, and ſpeciall Providence of God, of divers perſons to joyn themſelves with the Armies raiſed by the King, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Forces raiſed by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> with the Suburbs, and by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40426:6"/> Arms to force the Parliament: And the ſaid Lords and Commons finding by conſtant experience, that many wayes of force and treachery are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually attempted, to bring to utter ruine and deſtruction the Parliament and Kingdom, and that which is dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, the true Proteſtant Religion: And that for the preventing, and withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame, they have thought fit, That all who are true hearted, and lovers of their Countrey, ſhould binde themſelves each to other in a ſacred Vow and Covenant, in manner and form as followeth, and accordingly:</p>
            <div type="oath">
               <p>I <hi>A. B.</hi> in humility and reverence of the Divine Majeſty, declare my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſorrow for my own ſins, and the ſins of this Nation, which have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Calamities and Iudgements that now lie upon it; And my true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is, by Gods grace to endeavor the amendment of my own wayes; And that I do abhor and deteſt the ſaid wicked and treacherous Deſign lately diſcovered; And that I never gave nor will give my aſſent to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40426:6"/> execution thereof, but will according to my power and Vocation, oppoſe and reſiſt the ſame, and all other of the like nature: And in caſe any other like Deſign ſhall hereafter come to my knowledge, I will make ſuch timely diſcovery as I ſhall conceive may beſt conduce to the preventing thereof. And whereas I do in my conſcience beleeve, That the Forces Raiſed by the two Houſes of Parliament are raiſed and continued for their juſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and for the Defence of the true Proteſtant Religion and Liberties of the Subject, againſt the Forces raiſed by the King: I do here in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Almighty God, Declare, Vow, and Covenant, That I will, according to my power and vocation, aſſiſt the Forces raiſed and continued by both Houſes of Parliament, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Forces raiſed by the King without their conſent; and will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe aſſiſt all other perſons that ſhall take this Oath, in what they ſhall do in purſuance thereof; And will not directly or indirectly adhere unto, nor ſhall willingly aſſiſt the Forces
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40426:7"/> raiſed by the King without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of both Houſes of Parliament. And this Vow and Covenant I make in the preſence of Almighty God, the Searcher of all hearts, with a true intention to perform the ſame, as I ſhall anſwer at the great Day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Scripture">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40426:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>COme, let us joyn our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall Covenant, that ſhall not be forgotten,</hi> Iere. 50. 5. <hi>Take away the wicked from before the King, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> Prov. 25. 5. <hi>And all Judah re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced at the Oath, for they had ſworn with all their heart, and ſought him with their whole deſire, and he was found of them; and the Lord gave them reſt round about,</hi> 2 Chron. 15. 15.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discussion">
            <head>The excellent Uſefulneſſe of this COVENANT.</head>
            <p>VNion with God, Conformity to God, and Vnity of the three Kingdoms, are things moſt deſireable: In the firſt we are happy: In the ſecond holy: In the third is ſtrength, peace and ſafety. Theſe are the kindly fruits of this Covenant, and a Covenant that brings forth theſe, how gladly ſhould it be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40426:8"/> embraced, and how willingly received? They are lovely Bands that binde us to be happy, holy, and ſafe. The heart of man is backſliding, and a Covenant is like a hedge or wall to ſtop us from going back: it being a good and ready anſwer to a tempter or tentation: How ſhall I do this, and break my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? Surely we have been too looſe toward God, having almoſt loſt a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, too looſe in our lives, and too diſ-united among our ſelves: and well it may be thought, that a main end of this Rod which now lyes upon us, is to beat us into this Covenant; that thereby we may be knit faſter to God, to holineſſe, and each to other by this Band of Vnity. Yet the taking, is not the chief part of a Covenant, but the keeping. The benefits of a Covenant are then ſure and ſtedfaſt to us, when we are ſtedfaſt in the Covenant: Now a main cauſe of unſtedfaſtneſſe in the Covenant, is forgetfulneſſe of it. To prevent this, the Covenant is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this form that being ſet up before us, it may be daily ſeen, and by ſeeing remembred, and by remembring per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40426:8"/> And withall let us remember this; that all the wayes of God are mercy and truth to them that fear him and keep his Covenant. But becauſe no man is ſtrong in his own ſtrength, let us ſeek ſtrength of Him who is both our ſtrength and our Redeemer, that by Him we may be enabled to keep our Covenant with him, that ſo he may delight to dwell with us, to be called our God, and to call us his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; upon which happy condition, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Peace, Proſperity, and all bleſſings of Heaven and Earth, temporall and eternall.</p>
            <div type="resolution">
               <p>
                  <hi>VVEE Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Gospel, and Commons of all ſorts in the Kingdoms of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>by the Providence of God, living under one King, and being of one Reformed Religion, having before our eyes the glory of God, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the honour and happineſſe of the Kings Majeſty, and His Poſterity, and the true publique Liherty,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40426:9"/> 
                  <hi>Safety and Peace of the Kingdoms, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every ones private condition is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and calling to minde the treacherous and bloody plots, conspiracies, attempts, and practices of the Enemies of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true Religion, and profeſſours thereof in all places, especially in theſe three Kingdoms ever ſince the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion, and how much their rage, power and preſumption, are of late, and at this time increaſed and exerciſed; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the deplorable eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>the diſtreſſed eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>and the dangerous eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, <hi>are preſent, &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Teſtimonies; we have now at laſt, (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter other means of Supplication, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, Proteſtations, and Sufferings) for the preſervation of our ſelves &amp; our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, from utter ruine and Deſtruction, according to the commendable practice of theſe Kingdoms in former times, and the Example of Gods people in other Nations; after mature deliberation, reſolved and determined to enter into a mutuall and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne League and Covenant, wherein we all ſubſcribe, and each one of us for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40426:9"/> with our hands lifted up to the moſt high God, do Swear:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="oath">
               <p n="1">I. THat we ſhall ſincerely, really &amp; conſtantly, through the Grace of God, indeavor in our ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places &amp; callings, the preſervation of the reformed religion in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and Government, againſt our common Enemies, the Reformation of Religion in the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of God, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the beſt Reformed Churches; And ſhall indeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to the neareſt Conjunction and Vniformity in Religion, Confeſſion of Faith, form of Church government, Directory for Worſhip and Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing: That we and our Poſterity after us, may as Brethren, live in Faith and Love, and the Lord may delight to dwell in the midſt of us.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That we ſhall in like manner, without reſpect of perſons, indeavour
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40426:10"/> the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, (that is, Church-government, by Arch Biſhops, Biſhops, their Chauncellors and Commiſſaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Arch-Deacons, and all other Eccleſiaſticall Officers depending on that Hierarchie) Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſm, Prophaneneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; leſt we partake in other mens ſins, and thereby be in danger to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of their plagues, and that the Lord may be one, and his Name one in the three Kingdoms.</p>
               <p n="3">III. We ſhall with the ſame ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, reality, and conſtancy, in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Vocations, endeavour with our Eſtates and Lives, murually to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Rights and Priviledges of the Parliament, and the Liberties of the Kingdoms, and to preſerve and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Kings Majeſties perſon and Authority, in the preſervation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the true Religion, and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Kingdoms, that the world may bear witneſſe with our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our loyalty, and that we have no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40426:10"/> thoughts or intentions to diminiſh his Majeſties juſt power and Greatneſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. We ſhall alſo with all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe endeavour the diſcovery of all ſuch as have been, or ſhall be Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries, Malignants, or evil Inſtruments, by hindring the Reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, dividing the King from his People, or one of the Kingdoms from another, or making any Faction or parties amongſt the people, contrary to this League and Covenant, that they may be brought to publique triall, and receive condigne puniſhment, as the degree of their offences ſhall require or deſerve, or the Supream Iudicatories of both Kingdoms reſpectively, or others, having power from them for that effect, ſhall judge convenient.</p>
               <p n="5">V. And whereas the happineſſe of a bleſſed Peace between theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, denied in former times to our Progenitors, is by the good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, granted unto us, and hath been lately concluded and ſettled by both Parliaments, we ſhall each one of us, according to our place and intereſt, endeavour that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40426:11"/> conjoyned in a firm Peace and Vnion to all Poſterity; And that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice may be done upon the wilfull Oppoſers thereof, in manner expreſſed in the preſent Articles.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. We ſhall alſo, according to our places and callings, in this Common Cauſe of Religion, Liberty and Peace of the Kingdoms, aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into this League and Covenant, in the maintaining and purſuing thereof, and ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves, directly or indirectly, by whatſoever combination, perſwaſion or terror, to be divided, and withdrawn from this bleſſed Vnion and Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whether to make defection to the contrary part, or give our ſelves to a deteſtable indifferency or neutrality in this Cauſe, which ſo much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the glory of God, the good of the Kingdoms, and Honour of the King; but ſhall all the dayes of our lives, zealouſly and conſtantly continue therein againſt all oppoſition, and promote the ſame according to our power, againſt all Lets and Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever; and what we are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40426:11"/> not able our ſelves to ſuppreſſe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, we ſhall reveale and make known, that it may be timely prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or removed; All which we ſhall do as in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>And becauſe theſe Kingdoms are guilty of many ſins and provocations againſt God and his Son Ieſus Chriſt, as is too manifeſt by our preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes and dangers, the fruits thereof: We profeſſe and declare before God and the world our unfained deſire to be humbled for our own ſins, and for the ſins of theſe Kingdoms, eſpecially, that we have not as we ought, valued the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpel, that we have not laboured for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity &amp; power thereof, and that we have not indeavoured to receive Chriſt in our hearts, nor to walk worthy of him in our lives, which are the cauſes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins and tranſgreſſions, ſo much abounding amongſt us; And our true and unfeigned purpoſe, deſire &amp; indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for our ſelves &amp; all others under our power &amp; charge, both in publique and in private, in all duties we owe to God and man, to amend our lives, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40426:12"/> each one to go before another in the example of a reall Reformation, that the Lord may turn away his wrath and heavy indignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Churches and Kingdoms in truth and peace. And this Covenant we make in the preſence of Almighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to perform the ſame, as we ſhall anſwer at that great Day, when the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed, Moſt humbly beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by his Holy Spirit for this end, and to bleſſe our deſires and proceedings with ſuch ſucceſſe, as may be deliverance and ſafety to his people, and incouragement to other Chriſtian Churches, groaning under, or in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the yoak of Antichriſtian tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; to joyn in the ſame, or like Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Covenant, to the glory of God, the inlargement of the Kingdom of Ieſus Chriſt, and the Peace and Tranquility of Chriſtian Kingdoms and Common wealths.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40426:12"/>
            <head>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament; With Inſtructions for the taking of the <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas a Covenant for the preſervation and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion, The maintenance and defence of Laws and Liberties, hath been thought a fit and excellent meanes to acquire the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Almighty God towards the three Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and likewiſe to Vnite them, and by uniting, to ſtrengthen and fortifie them againſt the Common-Enemy of the true Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40426:13"/> peace, and proſperity of theſe Kingdoms; And whereas both Houſes of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> have already taken the ſame; It is now Ordered and Ordained by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, That the ſame Covenant be ſolemnly taken in all places throughout the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales.</hi> And for the better and more orderly taking thereof, theſe directions enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are appointed and enjoined ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be followed,</p>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40426:13"/>
               <head>Inſtructions for the taking of the Solemne League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</head>
               <p n="1">I. THat the Speakers of both Houſes of Parliament do ſpeedily ſend (to the Lord Generall, and all other Commanders in chief, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Townes, Forts, Caſtles, and Garriſons, as alſo to the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> Lord High Admirall of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land)</hi> true Copies of the Solemne League and Covenant, to the end it may be taken by all Officers and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers under their ſeverall Commands.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That all the Knights and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes now in Parliament, do take ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care ſpeedily to ſend down into their ſeverall Counties (which are or ſhall hereafter be under the power of the Parliament) a competent number of true Copies of the ſaid League and Covenant, unto the Committees of Parliament in their ſeverall Counties; And that the ſaid Committees do
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40426:14"/> within ſix dayes at the moſt diſperſe the ſaid Copies to every pariſh church or Chappel in the ſeverall Counties, to be delivered unto the Miniſters, Church-wardens, or Conſtables of the ſeverall Pariſhes.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That the ſaid Committees be required to return a certificate of the day when they received the ſaid co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, as alſo the day they ſent them forth, and to what Pariſhes they have ſent them, which certificate they are to return to the Clerk of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appointed for the Commons Houſe, that ſo an accompt may be given of it, as there ſhall be occaſion.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. That the ſeverall Miniſters be required to read the ſaid Covenant publikely unto their people the next Lords day after they receive it, and prepare their people for it, againſt the time that they ſhalbe called to take it.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That the ſaid League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant be taken by the Committees of Parliament in the place where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and tendred alſo to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Town, within ſeven daies after it comes to the ſaid Committees hands.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40426:14"/> VI. That the ſaid Committees, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have taken it themſelves, do ſpeedily diſperſe themſelves through the ſaid counties, ſo as three or four of them be together on dayes appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the chief places of meeting for the ſeverall diviſions of the ſaid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; And ſummon all the Miniſters, Church wardens, Conſtables, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers unto that place; where, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Sermon preached by one appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Committee for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they cauſe the ſame Miniſter to tender the League and Covenant unto all ſuch Miniſters and other Officers, to be taken and ſubſcribed by them, in the preſence of the ſaid Committees.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. That the ſaid Committees do withall give the ſaid Miniſters in Charge to tender it unto all the reſt of their Pariſhioners the next Lords Day, making then unto their ſaid Pariſhioners ſome ſolemn exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation concerning the taking and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving therof; and that the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees do alſo return to the ſeverall Pariſhes, the names of all ſuch as have taken the Covenant before them, who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40426:15"/> yet ſhall alſo ſubſcribe their names in the Book or Roll with their neighbors in their ſeverall Pariſhes: And if any Miniſter refuſe or neglect to appear at the ſaid ſummons, or refuſe to take the ſaid Covenant before the Committee, or to tender it to his Pariſh, that then the Committees be carefull to appoint another Miniſter to do it in his place.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. That the League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant be tendred to all men, within the ſeverall Pariſhes, above the age of eighteen as wel lodgers as inhabitants.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. That it be recommended to the earl of <hi>Manchester,</hi> to take ſpeciall care that it be tendered and taken in the Vniverſity of Cambridge.</p>
               <p n="10">X. That for the better incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſorts of Perſons to take it; It be recommended to the aſſembly of Divines to make a brief Declaration, by way of Exhortation, to all ſorts of Perſons to take it as that which they judge not only lawfull, But, (all things conſidered) exceeding expedient and neceſſary, for all that wiſh well to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the King and Kingdom to joyn in, and to be a ſingular pledge of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40426:15"/> Gods gracious goodneſſe to all the three Kingdoms.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. That if any Miniſter do refuſe to take, or to tender the Covenant, or any other perſon or perſons do not take it the Lords day that it is tendred, that then it be tendred to them again the Lords day following, and if they ſtill continue to refuſe it, that then their names be returned by the Miniſter that tenders it, and by the Church-wardens, or Conſtables unto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, and by them to the Houſe of Commons, that ſuch further courſe may be taken with them, as the Houſes of Parliament ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. That all ſuch perſons as are within the ſeverall Pariſhes, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice is given of the taking of it, and do abſent themſelves from the Church at the time of taking it, and come not in afterwards to the Miniſter &amp; Church-wardens, or other Officers to take it in their preſence before the return be made, be returned as refuſers.</p>
               <p>The manner of the taking it to be thus: <hi>The Miniſter to read the whole Covenant distinctly and audibly in the</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40426:16"/> 
                  <hi>Pulpit, and during the time of reading thereof, the whole Congregation to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and at the end of his reading thereof, all to take it ſtanding, lifting up their Right hands bare, and then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to ſubſcribe it ſeverally by writing their names (or their marks, to which their names are to be added) in a parchment Roll, or a Bock, wherein to the Covenant is to be inſerted, purpoſely provided for that end, and kept as a Record in the Pariſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">XIIII. That the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines do prepare an Exhortation for the better taking of the Covenant: And that the ſaid Exhortation and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> joyned in the Armies, for the vindication and defence of their Religion, Liberties and Lawes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Popiſh Prelaticall and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant party, and paſſed the 30. of <hi>Ian.</hi> laſt, be publikely read, when the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is read, according to the fourth and ſixth Articles: And that a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent number of Copies of the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration be ſent by the perſons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſend the true Copies of the ſaid Covenant, in the firſt and ſecond Articles.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40426:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Exhortation to the taking of the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for Reformation and Defence of Religion, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and happineſſe of the King, and the Peace and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the three Kingdoms of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
            <p>IF the power of Religion, or ſolid Reaſon, if Loyalty to the King, and piety to their native Countrey, or love to themſelves, and naturall affection to their poſterity, if the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of men touched with a deep ſenſe of all theſe, or Extraordinary ſucceſſe from God thereupon, can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken an embroyled bleeding rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to imbrace the ſoveraigne and onely means of their recovery there can be no doubt but this Solemn
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40426:17"/> League and Covenant wil find where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it ſhall be tendred, a people ready to entertain it with all cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and duty.</p>
            <p>And were it not commended to the Kingdom by the concurrent encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the Honourable Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, the Aſſembly of Divines, the renowned City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> multitudes of other perſons of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent rank and quality in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the whole Body of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who have all willingly ſworn and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it, with rejoycing at the Oath, ſo graciouſly ſeconded from Heaven already, by blaſting the Counſels, and breaking the power of the Enemy more than ever; yet it goeth forth in its own ſtrength, with ſuch convincing evidence of Equity, Truth and Righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may raiſe in all (not wilfully ignorant, or miſerably ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) inflamed affections to joyn with their Brethren in this happy Bond, for putting an end to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miſeries, and for ſaving both of King and Kingdom from utter ruine, now ſo ſtrongly and openly laboured
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40426:17"/> by the Popiſh faction, and ſuch as have been bewitched and beſotted by that viperous and bloody generation.</p>
            <p>For what is there almoſt in this Covenant, which was not for ſubſtance either expreſſed or manifeſtly inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that ſolemn <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 5. 1641. wherein the whole Kingdom ſtands ingaged untill this day? The ſinfull neglect whereof, doth (as we may juſtly fear) open one floodgage the more to let in all theſe calamities upon the Kingdom, and caſt upon it a neceſſity of renewing Covenant, and of entring into this.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, the extirpation of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, to wit, the whole Hierarchicall Government (ſtanding, as yet, by the known Laws of the Kingdom) is new, and unwarrantable: This will appear to all impartiall underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, (though new) to be not onely warrantable, but neceſſary; if they conſider (to omit what ſome ſay, that this Government was never formally Eſtabliſhed by any Laws of this Kingdom, at all) that the very life and ſoul thereof is already taken from it,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40426:18"/> by an Act paſſed this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo as (like <hi>Jezabels</hi> Carcaſſe, of which no more was left but the skull, the feet, and the palms of her hands) nothing of juriſdiction remains but what is precarious in them, and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary in thoſe who ſubmit unto them: that their whole Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is at beſt but a humane conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſuch as is found and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged by both Houſes of Parliament, (in which, the judgement of the whole Kingdome is involved and declared) not onely very prejudiciall to the Civill State, but a great hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance alſo to the perfect Reformation of Religion; Yea, who knoweth it not to be too much an enemy thereunto, and deſtructive to the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and pure adminiſtration of the Ordinances of Chriſt? which moved the well-affected, almoſt throughout this Kingdom, long ſince to Petition this Parliament (as hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired before, even in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and of King <hi>James)</hi> for a totall abolition of the ſame: Nor is any man hereby bound to offer
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40426:18"/> any violence to their perſons, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in his place and calling, to end ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their extirpation in a lawfull way.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe Clergy-men, who pretend that they (above all other) cannot <hi>Covenant</hi> to extirpate that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, becauſe they have (as they ſay) taken a ſolemn Oath to obey the Biſhops, <hi>in licitis &amp; honeſtis:</hi> They can tell, if they pleaſe, that they that have ſworn obedience to the Laws of the Land, are not thereby prohibited from indeavouring by all Lawfull means, the abolition of thoſe Laws, when they prove inconvenient or miſchievous. And if yet there ſhould any Oath be found, into which any Miniſters or others have entred, not warranted by the Laws of God and the Land, in this caſe, they muſt teach themſelves and others, that ſuch Oaths call for repentance, not pertinacy in them.</p>
            <p>If it be pleaded that this <hi>Covenant</hi> croſſeth the Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> there can be nothing further from truth: for, this <hi>Covenant</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:40426:19"/> bindes all, and more ſtrongly engageth them to <hi>preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties Perſon, and Authority, in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion and Liberties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſcruple, that this is done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kings conſent, will ſoon be removed, if it be remembred, that the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of the fifth of <hi>May</hi> before mentioned, was in the ſame manner voted and executed by both Houſes, and after (by order of one Houſe alone) ſent abroad to all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, His Majeſty not excepting againſt it, or giving any ſtop to the taking of it, albeit he was then Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Perſon at <hi>White-hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> drew all the people into a <hi>Covenant,</hi> without any ſpeciall Commiſſion from the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchs (then their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns) ſo to do, albeit they were not free Subjects, but Vaſſals, and one of them the meniall Servant of <hi>Artax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erxes,</hi> then by Conqueſt King of <hi>Judah</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Nor hath this doctrine or practiſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40426:19"/> been deemed ſeditious or warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the Princes that have ſate upon the Engliſh Throne, but juſtified and defended by <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memory, with the expence of much Treaſure and Noble blood, in the united Provinces of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> combined not onely without, but againſt the unjuſt violence of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain;</hi> King <hi>James</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſteps, ſo far as to approve their union, and to enter into League with them as free States; which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by His Majeſty now reigning, unto this day; who both by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition for relief of <hi>Rochell</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and his ſtrict confederacy with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the States Generall, notwithſtanding all the importunity of <hi>Spain</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, hath ſet to his Seal, that all that had been done by His Royall Anceſtors, in maintenance of thoſe who had ſo engaged and combined themſelves, was juſt and warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>And what had become of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Laws, and Liberties, of our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40426:20"/> Siſter Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> had they not entred into ſuch a ſolemn <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> at the beginning of the late troubles there; which courſe, however it was at firſt, by the Popiſh and Prelatick Projectors, repreſented to His Majeſty as an offence of the higheſt nature, juſtly deſerving cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement by the fury of a puiſſant Army; yet when the matter came afterwards in cool blood to be debated, firſt by Commiſſioners of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and then in open Parliament here, (when all thoſe of either Houſe, who are now engaged at <hi>Oxford,</hi> were preſent in Parliament, and gave their Votes therein) it was found, adjudged and declared by the King in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That our dear Brethren of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had done nothing, but what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Loyall and obedient Subjects, and were thereupon by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, publikely righted in all the Churches of this Kingdom, where they had been defamed.</p>
            <p>Therefore however ſome men, hoodwinkt and blinded, by the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of thoſe Ieſuiticall Engineers,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40426:20"/> who have long conſpired to ſacrifice our Religion to the Idolatry of <hi>Rome,</hi> our Laws, Liberties, and perſons to Arbitrary ſtavery, and our Eſtates to their inſatiable Avarice, may poſſibly be deterred and amuſed with high Threats and Declarations, flying up and down on the wings of the Royall Name and Countenance (now cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated and proſtituted to ſerve all their luſts) to Proclaim all Rebels and Traytors, who take this <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> yet let no faithfull Engliſh heart be afraid to joyn with our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of all the three Kingdoms in this Solemn <hi>League,</hi> as ſometimes the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (although under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King, did with the men of <hi>Judah)</hi> at the invitation of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>What though thoſe tongues ſet on fire by Hell do rail and threaten? That God who was pleaſed to clear up the innocency of <hi>Mordecai</hi> and the Iews againſt all the malicious aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of wicked <hi>Haman</hi> to his and their Soveraign, ſo as all his plotting produced but this effect, That <hi>when</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:40426:21"/> 
               <hi>the Kings commandment and decree drew neer to be put in execution, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Jews hoped to have power over them, it was turned to the contrary, and the Jews had rule over them that hated them, and laid hands on ſuch as ſought their hurt, ſo as no man could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, Eſth.</hi> 9. and that ſame God, who but even as yeſterday, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to diſperſe and ſcatter thoſe dark clouds and fogs which overſhadowed that Loyall and Religious Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to make their righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to ſhine as clear as the Sun at noon day, in the very eyes of their greateſt enemies, will doubtleſſely ſtand by all thoſe who with ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and a due ſenſe of their own ſins, and a neceſſity of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſhall now enter into an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <hi>Covenant</hi> with the Lord, never to be forgotten, to put an end to all thoſe unhappy and unnatural breaches between the King, and ſuch as are faithfull in the Land; cauſing their <hi>righteouſneſſe and praiſe to spring forth before all the Nations,</hi> to the terrour and confuſion of thoſe men of blood,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40426:21"/> the confederate enemies of God and the King, who have long combined, and have now raked together the dregs and ſcum of many Kingdoms, to bury all the glory, honour and liberty of this Nation, in the eternall Grave of diſhonour and deſtruction.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <head>Die Veneris, 9. Febr. 1643.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AN Exhortation touching the taking of the</hi> Solemn League <hi>and</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>and for ſatisfying of ſuch ſcruples, as may ariſe in the taking of it, was this day read the firſt and ſecond time; and by Vote upon the Queſtion aſſented unto, and Ordered to be forthwith Printed.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40426:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, for the better Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the</hi> LORDS-DAY.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the Lords day, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſeverall good Laws heretofore made, hath been not only greatly prophaned, but divers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Books have been publiſhed by the Prelaticall faction, againſt the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of that Day, and to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the prophanation of the ſame, to the manifeſt indangering of Souls, prejudice of the true Religion, great diſhonour of Almighty God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of his juſt wrath and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt this Land; The Lords and Commons for remedy thereof, do Order and Ordain, and be it Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and Ordained, That all the Laws enacted, and in force, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Obſervation of the Lords
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40426:22"/> day, be carefully put in execution; and that all and ſingular perſon and perſons whatſoever, ſhall on every Lords day, apply themſelves to the ſanctification of the ſame, by exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves thereon, in the duties of Piety and true Religion, publikely and privately: And that no perſon or perſons whatſoever, ſhall publikely cry, ſhew forth, expoſe to ſale, any Wares, Merchandizes, Fruit, Herbs, Goods or Chattels whatſoever, upon the Lords day, or any part thereof; upon pain, that every perſon ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſhall forfeit the ſame Goods ſo cryed, ſhewed forth, or put to ſale: And that no perſon or perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſhall, without reaſonable cauſe for the ſame, Travell, carry Burthens, or do any worldly labours, or work whatſoever, upon that day or any part thereof; upon pain, that every one travelling contrary to the meaning of this Ordinance, ſhall forfeit for every offence, ten ſhillings of lawfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and that every perſon carrying any burden, or doing any worldly labour or work, contrary to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40426:23"/> hereof, ſhall forfeit five ſhillings of like money for every ſuch offence. And be in further Ordained, That no perſon or perſons ſhall hereafter upon the Lords day, uſe, exerciſe, keep, maintain, or be preſent at any wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Shooting, Bowling, Ringing of Bells for pleaſure or paſtime, Maſque, Wake, otherwiſe called Feaſts, Church-Ale, Dancing, Games, Sport or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime whatſoever; upon pain, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon ſo offending, being above the age of Fourteen years, ſhall loſe and forfeit five ſhillings for every ſuch offence. And be it further Ordained, that all and ſingular perſon &amp; perſons, that have the care government, tuition or education of any childe or children, under or within the age of Fourteen years, ſhall forfeit and loſe twelve pence for every of the ſaid offences that ſhall be committed by any ſuch childe and children. And becauſe the prophanation of the Lords day hath been heretofore greatly occaſioned by May poles (a Heatheniſh vanity, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally abuſed to ſuperſtition and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe) The Lords and Commons
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40426:23"/> do further Order and Ordain, that all and ſingular May-poles, that are, or ſhall be erected, ſhall be taken down, and removed by the Conſtables, Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholders, Tything-men, petty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, and Church-wardens of the Pariſhes and places where the ſame be; and that no May-pole ſhall be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſet up, erected, or ſuffered to be within this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales.</hi> And it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordained, that if any of the ſaid Officers ſhall neglect to do their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the premiſſes, within one week after notice of this Ordinance, every of them for ſuch neglect ſhall forfeit five ſhillings of lawfull moneys; and ſo from week to week, weekly five ſhillings more afterwards, till the ſaid May-pole ſhall be taken down and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. And that if any Iuſtice of the Peace of the County, or the chief Officer or Officers, or any Iuſtice of the Peace, of, or within any City, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, or Town Corporate, where the ſaid offences ſhall be committed upon his or their view, or confeſſion of the party, or proof of any one or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40426:24"/> more witneſſes by oath (which the ſaid Iuſtice, chief Officer or Officers, is by this Ordinance authoriſed to miniſter) ſhall find any perſon offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the premiſſes, the ſaid Iuſtice, or chief Officer or Officers, ſhall give warrant under his or their hand and ſeal, to the Conſtables or Church-wardens of the Pariſh or Pariſhes where ſuch offence ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to ſeize the ſaid Goods, cryed, ſhewed forth, or put to ſale as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and to leavy the ſaid other forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or penalties by way of diſtreſſe, and ſale of the Goods of every ſuch offender, rendring to the ſaid offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the overplus of the moneys rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereby; And in default of ſuch diſtreſſe, or in caſe of inſufficiency, or inability of the offender to pay the ſaid forfeitures or penalties, that the party offending be ſet publikely in the Stocks by the ſpace of three hours; And all and ſingular, the forfeitures or penalties aforeſaid, ſhalbe imployed and converted to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh where the ſaid offences ſhall be committed, ſaving onely, that it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40426:24"/> ſhall and may be lawfull, to, and for any ſuch Iuſtice, Maior, or Head Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer or Officers, out of the ſaid for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures or penalties, to reward any perſon or perſons that ſhall inform of any offence againſt this Ordinance, according to their diſcretions; ſo as ſuch reward exceed not the third part of the forfeiture or penalties. And it is further Ordained by the ſaid Lords and Commons, that the Kings Declaration concerning obſerving of Wakes, and uſe of exerciſe and recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Lords day, The Book intituled, <hi>The Kings Maieſties Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to His Subiects, concerning lawfull Sports to be uſed;</hi> and all other Books and Pamphlets that have been, or ſhall be written, printed and publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Morality of the fourth Commandement, or of the Lords day, or to countenance the prophanation thereof, be called in, ſeized and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and publiquely butnt, by the Iuſtices of Peace, or ſome, or one of them, or by the chief Officer or Officers aforeſaid, in their ſeverall limits, or by their warrant or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40426:25"/> Provided, and be it Declared, That nothing in this Ordinance ſhall extend to the prohibiting of dreſſing of Meat in private Families, or the dreſſing and ſale of Victuals in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate way, in Innes or Victualling-houſes, for the uſe of ſuch as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cannot be provided for; or to the crying or ſelling of Milk before Nine of the clock in the Morning, or after Four of the clock in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, from the Tenth of <hi>September</hi> till the Tenth of <hi>March:</hi> or before Eight of the clock in the morning, or after five of the clock in the afternoon, from the Tenth of <hi>March</hi> till the Tenth of <hi>September.</hi> And whereas there is great breach of the Sabbath by Rogues, Vagabonds and Beggars, It is further Ordained, That the Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and all Iuſtices of Peace, Conſtables, Church-wardens, and other Officers and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters whatſoever, ſhall from time to time, cauſe all Laws againſt Rogues, Vagabonds and Beggars, to be put in due execution; and take order that all Rogues, Vagabonds and Beggars,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40426:25"/> do on every Sabbath day repair to ſome Church or Chappell, and remain there ſoberly and orderly during the time of Divine Worſhip And that all and ſingular perſon and perſons, that ſhall do any thing in the execution of this Ordinance, ſhall be protected and ſaved harmleſſe by the power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained, that this Ordinance be Printed and publiſhed, and read in all Pariſh Churches and Chappels, before the Sermon in the Morning, on ſome Lords day before the firſt of <hi>May</hi> next, on the South-ſide of Trent, and before the firſt of <hi>Iune</hi> next, on the North-ſide of Trent</p>
            <div type="order">
               <head>Die Sabbathi, 6. April, 1644.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ORdered by the</hi> Lords <hi>and</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <hi>Aſſembled in</hi> Parliament, <hi>That this Ordinance be printed and publiſhed, and read in all Churches and Chappels, before the Sermon in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, on ſome Lords day before the firſt of</hi> May <hi>next on the South-ſide of Trent; and before the firſt day of</hi> Iune <hi>next, on the North-ſide of Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40426:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, for the better Obſerving and Keeping a Monethly Faſt, within the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales.</head>
            <p>VVHereas the Kings Moſt Excellent Majeſty, upon the requeſt of the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, and by and with their advice and conſent, conſidering the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable and diſtreſſed condition of his good Subjects in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> (that there might be a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Humiliation of all the Eſtates of this Kingdom before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Almighty God in Faſting and Prayer) was graciouſly pleaſed to command the keeping of a Monethly Faſt; and to the end that all perſons might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40426:26"/> take notice thereof (and to leave ſuch without excuſe, as ſhould not duly keep and obſerve the ſame) did afterward by his Proclamation of the 8th of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1641. appoint that the ſame ſhould be generally, publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſolemnly holden, and kept, as well by abſtinence from food, as by publike prayers, preaching, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word of God, and other Religious and holy duties, in all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals, Collegiate and Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Chappels, within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> (without any exception) on the laſt Wedneſday of every Moneth, to continue during the troubles in the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland:</hi> All which his Majeſty did ſtraightly charge and command, ſhould be reverently and devoutly performed by all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as they deſire the bleſſing of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and would avoyd his heavy indignation againſt this Land and people; and upon pain of ſuch puniſhments as may juſtly be inflicted upon all ſuch as ſhall contemne or neglect ſo Religious a work and duty.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40426:27"/> And whereas the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in both Houſes of Parliament, have received divers informations from ſeverall parts of this Kingdom and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> of the great neglect of the due obſervation and keeping of the ſaid Faſt upon the dayes appointed, and of the propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the ſame, by many irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, ill-affected, looſe, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons, as well of the Clergy as others, who are ſo farre from af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting their ſoules, and looſing the bands of wickedneſſe, as that they provoke the wrath of Almighty God, and make ſo pious a meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his bleſſings, the occaſion of greater Iudgements.</p>
            <p>For the prevention whereof for the time to come, the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons do Order, Declare, Ordain, that in all and every the Cathedrals, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiate, and Pariſh Churches and Chappels, within the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> (without any exception) upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Lords day, next and immediately before any the dayes appointed for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40426:27"/> the ſaid publike Faſt, the Parſon, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car, Curate, or Miniſter, that upon that day ſhall Officiate, or exerciſe in any of the ſaid Cathedrals, Collegiate, Pariſh Churches or Chappels, ſhall give publike notice in every of the ſaid Cathedrals, Collegiate, Pariſh Churches or Chappels reſpectively, of the Faſt day next enſuing, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after Sermon, or prayer ended in the forenoon, before the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be diſmiſſed, carneſtly exhorting and perſwading all the people to the Solemne due keeping, and Religious obſervation of the whole day appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſaid Faſt, and that they would repair to ſome Church or Chappell, there diligently and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently to attend all ſuch holy duties as ſhall be uſed in the obſervance of the ſame; that they forbear to uſe all manner of ſports and paſtimes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and their ordinary Trades and callings upon the ſaid day, as well Carriers, Waggoners, Carters, Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n, Drovers, Butchers, Huckſters, Shop-keepers, Labourers; or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers uſing any Art, Trade, Miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40426:28"/> or manuall Occupation whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and that all Vintners, Taverners, Ale-houſe-keepers, and keepers of Victualling-houſes, do forbear to keep open their doors, Bulks, or Shops, or to ſell or utter (except in caſes of extream neceſſity) any Wine, Beer, Ale, or victuall, till the publike exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and Religious duties of that day in the reſpective Cathedrals, Collegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, Pariſh Churches and Chappels, be paſt and over.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, all and every the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Peace, Mayors, Bayliffs, Conſtables, Church-wardens, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers, inhabiting or reſiding within the limits or precincts of any ſuch Cathedrall, Collegiate, Pariſh Church or Chappell, are hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to take ſpeciall notice aſwell of ſuch Parſon, Vicar, Curate, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſter that ought to Officiate in any of the ſaid Cathedrals, Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giate, and Pariſh Churches or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, upon any ſuch day appointed for the ſaid Faſt, that ſhall either refuſe or neglect to do the ſame, or not do or cauſe the ſame to be done in that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40426:28"/> and ſolemn manner as it ought to be, or that ſhall refuſe to give notice of the Faſt day, at the time and in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as aforeſaid, and forthwith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn their names, and the names of all ſuch (from time to time) as ſhall wilfully offend herein, in contempt of the Laws, His Majeſty, and both Houſes of Parliament, unto ſome one or more of the Knights, Citizens, or Burgeſſes that ſerve for the county where ſuch offence is, or ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, that ſome ſpeedy courſe may be taken for the ſevere puniſhing of ſuch as ſhall offend herein according to the Laws.</p>
            <div type="order">
               <head>Die Mercurii, 22. Aug. 1642.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ordered by the Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, That this Ordinance be forthwith Printed and publiſhed:</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="resolution">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:40426:29"/>
               <head>24 <hi>April,</hi> 1643.</head>
               <p>VVHereas the Lords and Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have made an Ordinance for the more ſtrict and ſolemne keeping of the dayes of publike Faſt, which are not by all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons duly obſerved, even in theſe times of publike calamity, to the great diſhonour of God, and the contempt of the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now that more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar notice may be given unto all ſuch as ſhall offend herein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any exemplary puniſhment be inflicted upon them; It is ordered by the Commons now Aſſembled in Parliament, That all Conſtables (or their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) ſhall the day before every
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40426:29"/> publike Faſt, repair to every Houſe within their ſeverall and reſpective liberties, and charge all perſons, That they ſtrictly obſerve the Faſt, according to the directions in the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</p>
               <p>And they ſhall upon the ſaid dayes of the publike Faſt, walk through their ſaid liberties, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſearching for, and taking notice of all perſons, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by following their work of their calling, or ſitting in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns, Victualling or Alehouſes, or any other wayes ſhall not du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerve the ſame: And they are hereby required to return the Names of all ſuch perſons as they ſhall finde ſo offending, as alſo ſuch Informations as they ſhall receive againſt any other
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40426:30"/> perſons within their liberties, guilty of the like offence unto the Committee for Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſo they may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt for the contempt of the ſaid Ordinance; And all Conſtables are to obſerve theſe directions from time to time, ſo long as the ſaid publike Faſt ſhall be kept, without expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any further Order.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:40426:30"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
